<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-reddy-add-enterprise-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DoH/DoT in Enterprise Networks">DNS-over-HTTPS and
    DNS-over-TLS Server Deployment Considerations for Enterprise
    Networks</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>ADD</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses DoH/DoT deployment considerations for
      Enterprise networks. It particularly sketches the required steps to use
      DNS-over-TLS (DoT) and/or DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) server provided by the
      Enterprise network.</t>

      <t>One of the goals of the document is to assess to what extent existing
      tools can be used to provide such service.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC7626"></xref> discusses DNS privacy considerations
      in both "on the wire" (Section 2.4) and "in the server" (Section 2.5)
      contexts. In recent years there has also been an increase in available
      "public resolvers" <xref target="RFC8499"></xref> which DNS clients may
      use instead of the default resolvers provided by the network for a
      variety of reasons (e.g., offer a good reachability, support an
      encrypted transport, provide a strong privacy policy, (lack of)
      filtering).</t>

      <t>If public DNS over TLS (DoT) <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> or
      DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> servers are used
      instead of local DNS servers, it can adversely impact Enterprise
      network-based security. Typically, various network security services are
      provided by Enterprise networks to protect endpoints (e.g., laptops,
      printers, IoT devices). The network security services may, for example,
      prevent malware download, block known malicious URLs, enforce use of
      strong ciphers, stop data exfiltration, etc. Further, Enterprises
      network security services may enforce Acceptable Use Policy (AUP)
      according to the IT and workplace policies. For example, employees are
      not allowed to access some non-professional websites from the Enterprise
      network. These network security services act on DNS requests originating
      from endpoints. However, if an endpoint is configured to use public DoT
      or DoH servers, network security services cannot act on DNS requests
      from these endpoints without acting as a TLS proxy.</t>

      <t>In order to act on DNS requests from endpoints, network security
      services may block DoT traffic by dropping outgoing packets to
      destination TCP port number 853. Identifying DoH traffic is far more
      challenging than DoT traffic. Network security services may try to
      identify the well-known DoH resolvers by their domain name, and DoH
      traffic can be blocked by dropping outgoing packets to these domains.
      However, DoH traffic can not be fully identified without acting as a TLS
      proxy.</t>

      <t>If a network security service blocks access to the public DoH/DoT
      server, there are incompatibilities with the privacy profiles discussed
      in <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>: <list style="symbols">
          <t>If an endpoint has enabled strict privacy profile (Section 5 of
          <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>), the endpoint cannot resolve DNS
          names.</t>

          <t>If an endpoint has enabled opportunistic privacy profile (Section
          5 of <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>), endpoint will either fallback
          to an encrypted connection without authenticating the DNS server
          provided by the local network or fallback to clear text DNS, and
          cannot exchange encrypted DNS messages. The fallback adversely
          impacts security and privacy as internal attacks are possible in
          Enterprise networks. For example, an internal attacker can modify
          the DNS responses to re-direct the client to malicious servers or
          pervasively monitor the DNS traffic. The reader may refer to Section
          3.2.1 of <xref target="I-D.arkko-farrell-arch-model-t"></xref> for a
          discussion on the need for more awareness about attacks from within
          closed domains.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>To overcome the above threats, this document specifies mechanisms to
      configure endpoints to use Enterprise provided DoT and DoH servers, and
      bootstrap IoT devices and unmanaged endpoints to discover and
      authenticate the DoT and DoH servers provided by the Enterprise
      network.</t>

      <t>This document focuses on Enterprise networks, DoH/DoT sever discovery
      considerations for home networks are discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.btw-add-home"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter"></xref>.</t>

      <t>'DoH/DoT' refers to DNS-over-HTTPS and/or DNS-over-TLS.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="depl" title="IT-owned devices">
      <t>If a device is managed by an enterprise's IT department, the device
      can be configured to use Enterprise-provided DoH/DoT servers. This
      configuration might be manual or rely upon a device management software
      tool deployed by the Enterprise. For example, customizing Firefox using
      Group Policy to use the Enterprise DoH server is discussed in <xref
      target="Firefox-Policy"></xref> for Windows and MacOS, and setting
      Chrome policies is discussed in <xref
      target="Chrome-Policy"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IoT Devices">
      <t>Installing host agents may not be a viable option on IoT devices and
      network-based security is an efficient means to protect such IoT
      devices. If an IoT device is configured to use public DoT or DoH
      servers, and if a policy enforcement point in the local network is
      programmed using, for example, a Manufacturer Usage Description (MUD)
      file <xref target="RFC8520"></xref> by a MUD manager to only allow
      specific communications to and from the IoT device, the policy
      enforcement point cannot apply the network Access Control List (ACL)
      rules based on domain names (Section 8 of <xref
      target="RFC8520"></xref>).</t>

      <t>The following bootstrapping mechanisms can be used to securely
      provision IoT devices to use Enterprise provided DoT and DoH
      servers:<list style="symbols">
          <t>IoT devices supporting Bootstrapping Remote Secure Key
          Infrastructures (BRSKI) discussed in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref> can be
          bootstrapped with the Enterprise-provided DoH/DoT servers using the
          mechanism discussed in Section 5 of <xref
          target="I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server"></xref>.</t>

          <t><xref target="RFC8572"></xref> defines a bootstrapping strategy
          for enabling devices to securely obtain the required configuration
          information with no installer input, the onboarding information
          defined in Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC8572"></xref> can be
          extended to include the local DoH/DoT server information.</t>

          <t>The following discusses Wi-Fi authentication mechanisms supported
          by IoT devices:<vspace blankLines="1" />EAP-PSK <xref
          target="RFC4764"></xref> realizes mutual authentication and session
          key derivation using a Pre-Shared Key (PSK). Once the authentication
          is successful, EAP-PSK provides a protected communication
          channel.<vspace blankLines="1" />EAP-pwd <xref
          target="RFC8146"></xref> is another EAP method that utilizes a
          shared password for authentication using a PAKE scheme that is
          resistant to dictionary attacks. <vspace blankLines="1" />Not all of
          IoT devices support 802.1x supplicant and need an alternate
          mechanism to connect to the Enterprise network. To address this
          limitation, unique pre-shared keys are created for each IoT device
          and WPA-PSK is used. In other words, WPA-PSK is used with unique
          pre-shared keys for different IoT devices to deal with security
          issues. EAP-PSK/EAP-pwd/WPA-PSK seems to be a good choice on
          constrained devices. <list style="symbols">
              <t>For the above EAP methods and WPA-PSK, the IoT device needs
              to be provisioned with a PSK for mutual authentication. The PSK
              is only known to the IoT device and the EAP/WPA server. In this
              case, the bootstrapping mechanism discussed in Section 4 of
              <xref target="I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server"></xref> may
              be used to securely bootstrap IoT device with the authentication
              domain name (ADN) and DNS server certificate of the local
              network's DoH/ DoT server. It uses password-based authenticated
              key exchange (PAKE) scheme to authenticate the EST server and
              fetch the DoH/DoT server certificate.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If Device Provisioning Protocol (DPP) <xref target="dpp"></xref>
          is used, the configurator can securely configure IoT devices with
          the local DoH/DoT server using DPP.</t>

          <t>The OMA LWM2M specification <xref target="oma"></xref> defines an
          architecture where a new device (LWM2M client) contacts a
          Bootstrap-server which can provision IoT devices with the local
          DoH/DoT server.</t>

          <t>The Open Connectivitiy Foundation <xref target="ocf"></xref>
          defines the onboarding process. Once the onboarding tool and the new
          device have authenticated and established secure communication, the
          onboarding tool can provision the IoT device with the local DoH/DoT
          server.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document does not discuss opportunistic or leap-of-faith
      bootstrapping methods, they are susceptible to security issues (e.g.,
      IoT device can be configured with the attacker's DoH/DoT server or
      disable the use of DoH/DoT).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="BYOD">
      <t>The following mechanisms can be used to bootstrap BYOD (bring your
      own device):</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>If mobile device management (MDM) is used to secure BYOD, MDM can
          be used to configure OS/browser with the Enterprise provided DoH/DoT
          server.</t>

          <t>If an endpoint is on-boarded, for example, using Over-The-Air
          (OTA) enrollment to provision the device with a certificate and
          configuration profile, the configuration profile can include the URI
          of the DoH server and authentication domain name (ADN) of the DoT
          server. The OS/Browser can use the configuration profile to use the
          Enterprise provided DoH/DoT server. In this case, MDM is not
          installed on the device.</t>

          <t>If an endpoint uses the credentials (username and password)
          provided by the IT admin to mutually authenticate to the Enterprise
          WiFi Access Point, the boostrapping mechanism discussed in Section 4
          of <xref target="I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server"></xref> can
          be used to securely bootstrap the endpoint with the ADN and DNS
          server certificate of the local network's DoH/DoT server. <vspace
          blankLines="1" />The DNS client uses PAKE scheme to authenticate the
          EST server using the credentials to authenticate to the network. In
          this case, the endpoint is neither provisioned with a configuration
          profile or MDM is installed on the device. Many users have privacy
          and personal data sovereignty concerns with employers installing MDM
          on their personal devices; they are concerned that admin can glean
          personal information and could control how they use their devices.
          Yet when users do not install MDM on their devices, IT admins do not
          get visibility into the security posture of those devices.<vspace
          blankLines="1" />To overcome this problem, a host agent can
          cryptographically attest the security status associated with device,
          such as minimum passcode length, biometric login enabled, OS version
          etc. This approach is fast gaining traction especially with the
          advent of closed OS like <xref target="win10s">Windows 10 in S
          mode</xref> or <xref target="Chromebook">Chromebook</xref>, where
          applications are sandboxed (e.g., ransomware attack is not possbile)
          and applications can only be installed via the OS store.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The mechanism defined in <xref
      target="I-D.reddy-dprive-dprive-privacy-policy"></xref> can be used by
      the DNS server to communicate its privacy statement URL and filtering
      policy to a DNS client. This communication is cryptographically signed
      to attest to its authenticity.</t>

      <t>The DNS client can validate the signatory (i.e., cryptographically
      attested by the Organization hosting the DoH/DoT server) and the user
      can review human-readable privacy policy information of the DNS server
      and assess whether the DNS server performs DNS-based content
      filtering.</t>

      <t>If the discovered DoH/DoT server does not meet the privacy preserving
      data policy and filtering requirements of the user, the user can
      instruct the DNS client to take appropriate actions. For example, the
      action can be to use the local DNS server only to access internal-only
      DNS names and use another DNS server (adhering with his/her
      expectations) for public domains.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Mohamed Boucadair for the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8484'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7858'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8499'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8520'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4764'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8146'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7626' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8572' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.btw-add-home'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.reddy-dprive-dprive-privacy-policy'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.arkko-farrell-arch-model-t'
?>

      <reference anchor="Firefox-Policy"
                 target="ttps://github.com/mozilla/policy-templates/blob/master/README.md#dnsoverhttps">
        <front>
          <title>Policy templates for Firefox</title>

          <author></author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="dpp"
                 target="https://www.wi-fi.org/download.php?file=/sites/default/files/private/Device_Provisioning_Protocol_Specification_v1.1_1.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Wi-Fi Device Provisioning Protocol (DPP)</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="Specifictaion version 1.1">
            <organization>Wi-Fi Alliance</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="2018" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Wi-Fi Alliance" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="oma"
                 target="http://www.openmobilealliance.org/release/LightweightM2M/V1_1_1-20190617-A/OMA-TS-LightweightM2M_Core-V1_1_1-20190617-A.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Lightweight Machine to Machine Technical Specification:
          Core</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="Approved Version: 1.1.1 - 2019 06 17">
            <organization>Open Mobile Alliance</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2019" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Open Mobile Alliance" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ocf"
                 target="https://openconnectivity.org/specs/OCF_Security_Specification_v1.0.0.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>OCF Security Specification</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="Version: 1.0.0">
            <organization>Open Connectivity Foundation</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2017" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Open Connectivitiy Foundation" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chrome-Policy"
                 target="https://support.google.com/chrome/a/answer/2657289?hl=en">
        <front>
          <title>Chrome policies for users or browsers</title>

          <author>
            <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="win10s"
                 target="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/s-mode">
        <front>
          <title>Windows 10 in S mode</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chromebook"
                 target="https://support.google.com/chromebook/answer/3438631?hl=en">
        <front>
          <title>Chromebook security</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <!---->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
