<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-add-server-policy-selection-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DNS Server Info with Assertion Token">DNS Server Selection:
    DNS Server Information with Assertion Token</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael C. Richardson" initials="M."
            surname="Richardson">
      <organization>Sandelman Software Works</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mcr+ietf@sandelman.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>ADD WG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The document defines a mechanism that allows communication of DNS
      resolver information to DNS clients for use in selection decisions. In
      particular, the document defines a mechanism for a DNS server to
      communicate its filtering policy and privacy statement URL to DNS
      clients. This information is cryptographically signed to attest its
      authenticity. Such information is used for the selection of DNS
      resolvers. Typically, evaluating the DNS privacy statement, filtering
      policy, and the signatory, DNS clients with minimum human intervention
      can select the DNS server that best supports the user's desired privacy
      and filtering policy.</t>

      <t>This assertion is useful for DNS-over-TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS servers
      that are either public resolvers or are discovered in a local
      network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC7626"></xref> discusses DNS privacy considerations
      in both "on the wire" (Section 2.4 of <xref target="RFC7626"></xref>)
      and "in the server" (Section 2.5 of <xref target="RFC7626"></xref>)
      contexts. Two protocols that provide encrypted channels between DNS
      clients and servers are DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref> and DNS-over-TLS (DoT) <xref
      target="RFC7858"></xref>.</t>

      <t>DNS clients can discover and authenticate DoH and DoT servers
      provided by a local network, for example using the techniques proposed
      in <xref target="I-D.btw-add-home"></xref>. If the mechanism used to
      discover the DoH/DoT server is insecure, the DNS client needs evidence
      about the DoH/DoT server to assess its trustworthiness and a way to
      appraise such evidence. The mechanism specified in this document can be
      used by the DNS client to cryptographically identify it is connecting to
      a DoT/DoH server hosted by a specific organization (e.g., ISP or
      Enterprise).</t>

      <t>The DNS Recursive Operator Privacy (DROP) statement explained in
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-dprive-bcp-op"></xref> outlines the recommended
      contents a DNS operator should publish, thereby providing a means for
      users to evaluate the privacy properties of a given DNS service. While a
      human can review the privacy statement of a DNS server operator, the
      challenge is the user has to search to find the URL that points to the
      human readable privacy policy information of the DNS server. Also, a
      user does not know if a DNS server (public or local) performs DNS-based
      content filtering.</t>

      <t>This document simplifies the user experience by supporting a
      mechanism to retrieve the DNS server policy permitting the user to
      review human-readable privacy policy information of the DNS server and
      to assess whether that DNS server performs DNS-based content
      filtering.</t>

      <t>This document also defines a mechanism for DNS clients to gather a
      set of information related to discovered (or pre-configured) servers and
      use that information to fed a DNS server selection procedure. The
      following parameters are supported in this version:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Malware blocking:">Indicates whether the DNS server
          offers malware blocking service.</t>

          <t hangText="Policy blocking:">Indicates whether the DNS server
          maintains a block-list (e.g., imposed by regulation).</t>

          <t hangText="QNAME minimization:">Indicates whether the DNS server
          implements QNAME minimisation <xref target="RFC7816"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The cryptographically signed policy allows a DNS client to, e.g.,
      connect to multiple DNS servers and prompt the user to review the DNS
      privacy statements to select the DNS server that adheres to the privacy
      preserving data policy and DNS filtering expectations of the user. How a
      user instructs a DNS client about his/her preferences and how/whether
      the DNS client prompts a user are out of scope.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scope" title="Sample Use Cases ">
      <t>The mechanism for a DNS server to communicate its cryptographically
      signed policies to DNS clients contributes to solve the following
      problems in various deployments:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The DoH/DoT server advertised using DHCP/RA in Home and Mobile
          networks is insecure, the mechanism specified in this document can
          be used by the DNS client to validate the signatory (e.g.,
          cryptographically attested by the ISP).</t>

          <t>Typically Enterprise networks do not assume that all devices in
          their network are managed by the IT team or Mobile Device Management
          (MDM) devices, especially in the quite common BYOD (Bring Your Own
          Device) scenario. The mechanism specified in this document can be
          used by users of the BYOD devices to determine if the DNS server on
          the local network complies with their user's privacy policy and DNS
          filtering expectations.</t>

          <t>The user selects specific well-known networks (e.g., organization
          for which a user works or a user works temporarily within another
          corporation) to learn the privacy policy statement and filtering
          policy of the local DNS server. If the discovered DoH/DoT server
          does not meet the privacy preserving data policy and filtering
          requirements of the user, the DNS client can take appropriate
          actions. For example, the action can be to use the discovered DNS
          server only to access internal-only DNS names and use another DNS
          server (adhering with the user's expectations) for public
          domains.</t>

          <t>The policy information signals the presence of DNS-based content
          filtering in the attached network. If the network is well-known to
          the DNS client and the local DNS server meets the privacy
          requirements of the user, the DNS client can continue to use
          encrypted connection with the local DoH/DoT server. If the error
          code returned by the DNS server indicates access to the domain is
          blocked because of internal security policy <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-extended-error"></xref>, the DNS client can
          securely identify access to the domain is censored by the
          network.</t>

          <t>The signed policy contains an URL that points to a human-readable
          privacy policy information of the DNS server for the user to review
          and can make an informed decision whether the DNS server is
          trustworthy to honor the privacy of the user. The DNS Push
          Notifications mechanism defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-push"></xref> can be used by the DNS client
          to be asynchronously notified when the policy change occurs. The
          client automatically learns updates to the policy of the DNS server,
          and whenever the privacy statement of the DNS server changes, the
          client can notify the user to re-evaluate the updated privacy
          statement. As a reminder, DNS Push Notification is only defined for
          TLS over TCP. DNS client implementations that do not support DNS
          Push Notifications can use the mechanism discussed in <xref
          target="exp-header-parameter"></xref> to identify policy
          updates.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter"></xref>.</t>

      <t>'DoH/DoT' refers to DNS-over-HTTPS and/or DNS-over-TLS.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="PAT" title="Policy Assertion Token (PAT): Overview">
      <t>JSON Web Token (JWT) <xref target="RFC7519"></xref> and JSON Web
      Signature (JWS) <xref target="RFC7515"></xref> and related
      specifications define a standard token format that can be used as a way
      of encapsulating claimed or asserted information with an associated
      digital signature using X.509 based certificates. JWT provides a set of
      claims in JSON format that can accommodate asserted policy information
      of the DoH/DoT server. Additionally, JWS provides a path for updating
      methods and cryptographic algorithms used for the associated digital
      signatures.</t>

      <t>JWS defines the use of JSON data structures in a specified canonical
      format for signing data corresponding to JOSE header, JWS Payload, and
      JWS Signature. The next sections define the header and claims that MUST
      be minimally used with JWT and JWS for privacy assertion token.</t>

      <t>The Policy Assertion Token (PAT) specifically uses this token format
      and defines claims that convey the policy information of DoH/DoT server.
      After the DoT/DoH session is established, the client can retrieve the
      PAT object using the RESINFO RRtype and QNAME of "resolver-info.arpa/IN"
      defined in <xref target="I-D.pp-add-resinfo"></xref>. The signature of
      PAT object can be validated by the DNS client. If the signer and the
      contents of the PAT object comply with the user's requirements, the
      user's client software can use that DNS server.</t>

      <t>The PAT object is signed by the DNS server's domain that is
      authoritative to assert the DNS server policy information. This
      authority is represented by the certificate credentials and the
      signature.</t>

      <t>For example, the PAT object could be created by the organization
      hosting the DoH/DoT server and optionally by a third party who performed
      privacy and security audit of the DoH/DoT server. The DNS client needs
      to have the capability to verify the digital signature and to parse the
      PAT object.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pat_header" title="PAT Header">
      <t>The JWS token header is a JOSE header (Section 4 of <xref
      target="RFC7515"></xref>) that defines the type and encryption algorithm
      used in the token.</t>

      <t>PAT header MUST include, at a minimum, the header parameters defined
      in Sections <xref format="counter"
      target="typ-type-header-parameter"></xref>, <xref format="counter"
      target="alg-algorithm-header-parameter"></xref>, and <xref
      format="counter" target="x5u-x509-url-header-parameter"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="typ-type-header-parameter"
               title="'typ' (Type) Header Parameter">
        <t>The 'typ' (Type) Header Parameter is defined Section 4.1.9 of <xref
        target="RFC7515"></xref> to declare the media type of the complete
        JWS.</t>

        <t>For PAT Token the 'typ' header MUST be the string 'pat'. This
        represents that the encoded token is a JWT of type pat.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="alg-algorithm-header-parameter"
               title="'alg' (Algorithm) Header Parameter">
        <t>The 'alg' (Algorithm) Header Parameter is defined in Section 4.1.1
        of <xref target="RFC7515"></xref>. It specifies the JWS signature
        cryptographic algorithm. It also refers to a list of defined 'alg'
        values as part of a registry established by JSON Web Algorithms (JWA)
        <xref target="RFC7518"></xref> Section 3.1.</t>

        <t>For the creation and verification of PAT tokens and their digital
        signatures, implementations MUST support ES256 as defined in Section
        3.4 of <xref target="RFC7518"></xref>. Implementations MAY support
        other algorithms registered in the JSON Web Signature and Encryption
        Algorithms registry created by <xref target="RFC7518"></xref>. The
        content of that registry may be updated in the future depending on
        cryptographic strength requirements guided by current security best
        practice. The mandatory-to-support algorithm for PAT tokens may
        likewise be updated in the future.</t>

        <t>Implementations of PAT digital signatures using ES256 as defined
        above SHOULD use deterministic ECDSA when supported for the reasons
        stated in <xref target="RFC6979"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="x5u-x509-url-header-parameter"
               title="'x5u' (X.509 URL) Header Parameter">
        <t>As defined in Section 4.1.5 of <xref target="RFC7515"></xref>, the
        'x5u' header parameter defines a URI <xref target="RFC3986"></xref>
        referring to the resource for the X.509 public key certificate or
        certificate chain <xref target="RFC5280"></xref> corresponding to the
        key used to digitally sign the JWS. Generally, as defined in Section
        4.1.5 of <xref target="RFC7515"></xref> this corresponds to an HTTPS
        or DNSSEC resource using integrity protection.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="example-pat-header" title="An Example of PAT Header">
        <t>An example of the PAT header is shown in <xref target="ex"></xref>.
        It includes the specified PAT type, ES256 algorithm, and an URI
        referencing the network location of the certificate needed to validate
        the PAT signature.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ex" title="A PAT Header Example">
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "typ":"pat",
  "alg":"ES256",
  "x5u":"https://cert.example.com/pat.cer"
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pat_payload" title="PAT Payload">
      <t>The token claims consists of the policy information of the DNS server
      which needs to be verified at the DNS client. These claims follow the
      definition of a JWT claim (Secion 4 of <xref target="RFC7519"></xref>)
      and are encoded as defined by the JWS Payload (Section 3 of <xref
      target="RFC7515"></xref>).</t>

      <t>PAT defines the use of a standard JWT-defined claim as well as custom
      claims corresponding to the DoT or DoH servers.</t>

      <t>Claim names MUST use the US-ASCII character set. Claim values MAY
      contain characters that are outside the ASCII range, however they MUST
      follow the default JSON serialization defined in Section 7 of <xref
      target="RFC7519"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="jwt-defined-claims" title="JWT Defined Claims">
        <section anchor="iat-issued-at-claim" title="'iat' - Issued At Claim">
          <t>The JSON claim MUST include the 'iat' (Section 4.1.6 of <xref
          target="RFC7519"></xref>) defined claim "Issued At". The 'iat'
          should be set to the date and time of issuance of the JWT. The time
          value should be of the format (NumericDate) defined in Section 2 of
          <xref target="RFC7519"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="exp-header-parameter"
                 title="'exp' - Expiration Time Claim">
          <t>The JSON claim MUST include the 'exp' (Section 4.1.4 of <xref
          target="RFC7519"></xref>) defined "claim Expiration Time". The 'exp'
          should be set to specify the expiration time on or after which the
          JWT is not accepted for processing. The PAT object should expire
          after a reasonable duration. A short expiration time for the PAT
          object periodically reaffirms the policy information of the DNS
          server to the DNS client and ensures the DNS client does not use
          outdated policy information. If the DNS client knows the PAT object
          has expired, it should make another request to get the new PAT
          object from the DNS server. For example, the client can compute a
          hash of the resolver information, retreive the information after the
          expiration time, computes the hash of the newly retrieved resolver
          information, and compares with the old hash to detect policy
          updates. A quality implementation can perform automatic analysis and
          avoid presenting this information to the user if the DNS server's
          policies have not changed.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pat_claims" title="PAT Specific Claims">
        <section anchor="server-identity" title="DNS Server Identity Claims">
          <t>The DNS server identity is represented by a claim that is
          required for PAT: the 'server' claim. The 'server' MUST contain
          claim values that are identity claim JSON objects where the child
          claim name represents an identity type and the claim value is the
          identity string, both defined in subsequent subsections. </t>

          <t>These identities can be represented as either authentication
          domain name (ADN) (defined in <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>) or
          Uniform Resource Indicators (URI). </t>

          <t>The DNS client constructs a reference identifier for the DNS
          server based on the ADN or the domain portion in the URI of the DNS
          server identity. The domain name in the DNS-ID identifier type
          within subjectAltName entry in the DNS server certificate conveyed
          in the TLS handshake is matched with the reference identifier. If
          the match is not successful, the client MUST not accept the PAT for
          further processing.</t>

          <section anchor="adn"
                   title="'adn' - Authentication Domain Name Identity">
            <t>If the DNS server identity is an ADN, the claim name
            representing the identity MUST be 'adn'. The claim value for the
            'adn' claim is the ADN.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="uri-identity" title="'uri' - URI Identity">
            <t>If the DNS server identity is of the form URI, as defined in
            <xref target="RFC3986"></xref>, the claim name representing the
            identity MUST be 'uri' and the claim value is the URI form of the
            DNS server identity.</t>

            <t>As a reminder, if DoH is supported by the DNS server, the DNS
            client uses the https URI scheme (Section 3 of <xref
            target="RFC8484"></xref>).</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policyinfo"
                 title="'policyinfo' (Policy Information) Claim">
          <t>The 'policyinfo' claim MUST be formatted as a JSON object. The
          'policyinfo' claim contains the policy information of the DNS
          server, it includes the following attributes:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="filtering:">If the DNS server changes some of the
              answers that it returns based on policy criteria, such as to
              prevent access to malware sites or objectionable content. This
              optional attribute has the following structure:<list
                  style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="malwareblocking:">The DNS server offers malware
                  blocking service. If access to domains is blocked on threat
                  data, the parameter value is set to 'true'.</t>

                  <t hangText="policyblocking:">If access to domains is
                  blocked on a blacklist or objectionable content, the
                  parameter value is set to 'true'.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t hangText="qnameminimization:">If the DNS server implements
              QNAME minimisation <xref target="RFC7816"></xref> to improve DNS
              privacy. If the parameter value is set to 'true', QNAME
              minimisation is supported by the DNS server. This is a mandatory
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="privacyurl:">A URL that points to the privacy
              policy information of the DNS server. This is a mandatory
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="auditurl:">A URL that points to the security
              (including privacy) assessment report of the DNS server by a
              third party auditor. This is an optional attribute.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="pat_payload_example" title="Example">
          <t><xref target="poex"></xref> shows an example of policy
          information.</t>

          <figure anchor="poex" title="An Example of Policy Information">
            <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "server":{
      "adn":["example.com"]
  },
  "iat":1443208345,
  "exp":1443640345,
  "policyinfo": {
     "filtering": {
         "malwareblocking": true,
         "policyblocking": false
     },
     "qnameminimization":false,
     "privacyurl": "https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/"
  } 
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pat_signature" title="PAT Signature">
      <t>The signature of the PAT is created as specified in Section 5.1 of
      <xref target="RFC7515"></xref> (Steps 1 through 6). PAT MUST use the JWS
      Protected Header.</t>

      <t>For the JWS Payload and the JWS Protected Header, the lexicographic
      ordering and white space rules described in <xref
      target="pat_header"></xref> and <xref target="pat_payload"></xref>, and
      JSON serialization rules in <xref target="json_serialization"></xref>
      MUST be followed.</t>

      <t>The PAT is cryptographically signed by the domain hosting the DNS
      server and optionally by a third party who performed privacy and
      security audit of the DNS server.</t>

      <t>The policy information is attested using "Organization Validation"
      (OV) or "Extended Validation" (EV) certificates to avoid bad actors
      taking advantage of this mechanism to advertise DoH/DoT servers for
      illegitimate and fraudulent purposes meant to trick DNS clients into
      believing that they are using a legitimate DoH/DoT server hosted to
      provide privacy for DNS transactions.</t>

      <t>Alternatively, a DNS client has to be configured to trust the leaf of
      the signer of the PAT object. That is, trust of the signer MUST NOT be
      determined by validating the signer via the OS or the browser trust
      chain because that would allow any arbitrary entity to operate a DNS
      server and assert any sort of policy.</t>

      <t><xref
      target="example-es256-based-pat-jws-serialization-and-signature"></xref>
      provides an example of how to follow the steps to create the JWS
      Signature.</t>

      <t>JWS JSON serialization (Step 7 in Section 5.1 of <xref
      target="RFC7515"></xref>) is supported for PAT to enable multiple
      signatures to be applied to the PAT object. For example, the PAT object
      can be cryptographically signed by the domain hosting the DNS server and
      by a third party who performed privacy and security audit of the DNS
      server.</t>

      <t><xref
      target="example-es256-based-pat-jws-serialization-and-signatures"></xref>
      includes an example of the full JWS JSON serialization representation
      with multiple signatures.</t>

      <t>Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC7515"></xref> (Step 8) describes the
      method to create the final JWS Compact Serialization form of the PAT
      Token.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="extending_pat" title="Extending PAT">
      <t>PAT includes the minimum set of claims needed to securely assert the
      policy information of the DNS server. JWT supports a mechanism to add
      additional asserted or signed information by simply adding new claims.
      PAT can be extended beyond the defined base set of claims to represent
      other DNS server information requiring assertion or validation.
      Specifying new claims follows the baseline JWT procedures (<xref
      target="RFC7519">Section 10.1 of </xref>). Understanding new claims on
      the DNS client is optional. The creator of a PAT object cannot assume
      that the DNS client will understand the new claims.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="json_serialization"
             title="Deterministic JSON Serialization">
      <t>JSON objects can include spaces and line breaks, and key value pairs
      can occur in any order. It is therefore a non-deterministic string
      format. In order to make the digital signature verification work
      deterministically, the JSON representation of the JWS Protected Header
      object and JWS Payload object MUST be computed as follows.</t>

      <t>The JSON object MUST follow the following rules. These rules are
      based on the thumbprint of a JSON Web Key (JWK) as defined in Section 3
      of <xref target="RFC7638"></xref> (Step 1).</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The JSON object MUST contain no whitespace or line breaks before
          or after any syntactic elements.</t>

          <t>JSON objects MUST have the keys ordered lexicographically by the
          Unicode <xref target="UNICODE"></xref> code points of the member
          names.</t>

          <t>JSON value literals MUST be lowercase.</t>

          <t>JSON numbers are to be encoded as integers unless the field is
          defined to be encoded otherwise.</t>

          <t>Encoding rules MUST be applied recursively to member values and
          array values.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section anchor="example-pat-deterministic-json-form"
               title="Example PAT Deterministic JSON Form">
        <t>This section demonstrates the deterministic JSON serialization for
        the example PAT Payload shown in <xref
        target="pat_payload_example"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The initial JSON object is shown in <xref
        target="initial"></xref>.</t>

        <figure anchor="initial" title="Initial JSON Object">
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "server":{
      "adn":["example.com"]
  },
  "iat":1443208345,
  "exp":1443640345,
  "policyinfo": {
     "qnameminimization":false,
     "privacyurl": "https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/"
  } 
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The parent members of the JSON object are as follows, in
        lexicographic order: "exp", "iat", "policyinfo", "server".</t>

        <t>The final constructed deterministic JSON serialization
        representation, with whitespace and line breaks removed, (with line
        breaks used for display purposes only) is:</t>

        <figure anchor="final" title="Deterministic JSON Form">
          <artwork><![CDATA[{"exp":1443640345,"iat":1443208345,
"policyinfo":{"privacyurl":"https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/",
"qnameminimization":false},"server":{"adn":["example.com"]}}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>Users are expected to indicate to their system in some way that they
      trust certain PAT signers (e.g., if working for Example, Inc., the
      user's system is configured to trust "example.com" signing the PAT). By
      doing so, the DNS client can automatically discover DoH/DoT server in
      specific networks, validate the PAT signature and the user can check if
      the human readable privacy policy information of the DNS server complies
      with user's privacy needs, prior to using that DoH/DoT server for DNS
      queries.</t>

      <t>The DNS client MUST retrieve the human-readable privacy statement
      from the 'privacyurl' attribute to assist with that decision (e.g.,
      display the privacy statement when it changes, show differences in
      previously-retrieved version, etc.). With the steps above, user can
      review the human-readable privacy policy information of the DoH/DoT
      server.</t>

      <t>Another scenario is bootstrapping a networking device to use the
      DoH/DoT server in the local network. Secure Zero Touch Provisioning
      <xref target="RFC8572"></xref> defines a bootstrapping strategy for
      enabling devices to securely obtain the required configuration
      information with no user input. If the DoH/DoT information is insecurely
      discovered and not pre-configured in the networking device, the client
      can validate the Policy Assertion Token signature using the owner
      certificate as per Section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC8572"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The use of PAT object based on the validation of the digital
      signature and the associated certificate requires consideration of the
      authentication and authority or reputation of the signer to attest the
      policy information of the DNS server being asserted. Bad actors can host
      DNS-over-TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS servers, and claim the servers offer
      privacy but exactly do the opposite to invade the privacy of the user.
      Bad actor can get a domain name, host DNS-over-TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS
      servers, and get the DNS server certificate signed by a CA. The policy
      information will have to be attested using OV/EV certificates or a PAT
      object signer trusted by the DNS client to prevent the attack. </t>

      <t>The CA that issued the OV/EV certificate does not attest the resolver
      information. The organization hosting the DNS server attests the
      resolver information using the OV/EV certificate and the client uses the
      OV/EV certificate to identify the organization (e.g., ISP or Enterprise)
      hosting the DNS server.</t>

      <t>If the PAT object is asserted by a third party, it can do a "time of
      check" but the DNS server is susceptible of "time of use" attack. For
      example, changes to the policy of the DNS server can cause a
      disagreement between the auditor and the DNS server operation, hence the
      PAT object needs to be also asserted by the domain hosting the DNS
      server. In addition, the PAT object needs to have a short expiration
      time (e.g., 7 days) to ensure the DNS server's domain re-asserts the
      policy information and limits the damage from change in policy and
      mis-issuance.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="media-type-registration"
               title="Media Type Registration">
        <section anchor="media-type-registry-contents-additions-requested"
                 title="Media Type Registry Contents Additions Requested">
          <t>This section registers the 'application/pat' media type <xref
          target="RFC2046"></xref> in the 'Media Types' registry in the manner
          described in <xref target="RFC6838"></xref>, which can be used to
          indicate that the content is a PAT defined JWT.</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Type name: application</t>

              <t>Subtype name: pat</t>

              <t>Required parameters: n/a</t>

              <t>Optional parameters: n/a</t>

              <t>Encoding considerations: 8bit; application/pat values are
              encoded as a series of base64url-encoded values (some of which
              may be the empty string) separated by period (&lsquo;.&rsquo;)
              characters..</t>

              <t>Security considerations: See the Security Considerations
              Section of <xref target="RFC7515"></xref>.</t>

              <t>Interoperability considerations: n/a</t>

              <t>Published specification: [TODO this document]</t>

              <t>Applications that use this media type: DNS</t>

              <t>Fragment identifier considerations: n/a</t>

              <t>Additional information: <vspace blankLines="1" /> Magic
              number(s): n/a File extension(s): n/a Macintosh file type
              code(s): n/a</t>

              <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further
              information: Tirumaleswar Reddy, kondtir@gmail.com</t>

              <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>

              <t>Restrictions on usage: none</t>

              <t>Author: Tirumaleswar Reddy, kondtir@gmail.com</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Provisional registration? No</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="json-web-token-claims-registration"
               title="JSON Web Token Claims Registration">
        <section anchor="registry-contents-additions-requested"
                 title="Registry Contents Additions Requested">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Claim Name: 'server'</t>

              <t>Claim Description: DNS server identity</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): <xref
              target="server-identity"></xref> of [TODO this document]</t>

              <t>Claim Name: 'policyinfo'</t>

              <t>Claim Description: Policy information of DNS server.</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): <xref target="policyinfo"></xref>
              of [TODO this document]</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="resolver-information"
               title="DNS Resolver Information Registration">
        <t>IANA will add the names filtering, qnameminimization, privacyurl
        and auditurl to the DNS Resolver Information registry defined in
        Section 4.2 of <xref target="I-D.pp-add-resinfo"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>This specification leverages some of the work that has been done in
      <xref target="RFC8225"></xref>. Thanks to Ted Lemon, Paul Wouters, Neil
      Cook and Shashank Jain for the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8484"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8499"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7515"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7519"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7518"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6979"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7638"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6838"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2046"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7858"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8310"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.pp-add-resinfo'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnssd-push'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7626"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7816"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8225"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8572"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.btw-add-home'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-extended-error' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-bcp-op'?>

      <reference anchor="UNICODE"
                 target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/latest/">
        <front>
          <title>The Unicode Standard</title>

          <author>
            <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="21" month="June" year="2016" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="example-es256-based-pat-jws-serialization-and-signature"
             title="Example ES256 based PAT JWS Serialization and Signature">
      <t>For PAT, there will always be a JWS with the following members:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>'protected', with the value BASE64URL(UTF8(JWS Protected
          Header))</t>

          <t>'payload', with the value BASE64URL (JWS Payload)</t>

          <t>'signature', with the value BASE64URL(JWS Signature)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This example will follow the steps in JWS <xref
      target="RFC7515"></xref> Section 5.1, steps 1-6 and 8 and incorporates
      the additional serialization steps required for PAT.</t>

      <t>Step 1 for JWS references the JWS Payload, an example PAT Payload is
      as follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "server":{
      "adn":["example.com"]
  },
  "iat":1443208345,
  "exp":1443640345,
  "policyinfo": {
     "filtering": {
         "malwareblocking": true,
         "policyblocking": false
     },
     "qnameminimization":false,
     "privacyurl": "https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/"
  } 
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This would be serialized to the form (with line break used for
      display purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[{"exp":1443640345,"iat":1443208345,"policyinfo":{
"filtering":{"malwareblocking": true,"policyblocking": false},
"privacyurl":"https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/",
"qnameminimization":false},"server":{"adn":["example.com"]}}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Step 2 Computes the BASE64URL(JWS Payload) producing this value (with
      line break used for display purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
eyJleHAiOjE0NDM2NDAzNDUsImlhdCI6MTQ0MzIwODM0NSwicG9saWN5aW5mbyI6e
yJmaWx0ZXJpbmciOnsibWFsd2FyZWJsb2NraW5nIjp0cnVlLCJwb2xpY3libG9ja2
luZyI6ZmFsc2V9LCJwcml2YWN5dXJsIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9jb21
taXRtZW50LXRvLXByaXZhY3kvIiwicW5hbWVtaW5pbWl6YXRpb24iOmZhbHNlfSwi
c2VydmVyIjp7ImFkbiI6WyJleGFtcGxlLmNvbSJdfX0


]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>For Step 3, an example PAT Protected Header comprising the JOSE
      Header is as follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "alg":"ES256",
  "typ":"pat",
  "x5u":"https://cert.example.com/pat.cer"
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This would be serialized to the form (with line break used for
      display purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{"alg":"ES256","typ":"pat","x5u":"https://cert.example.com
/pat.cer"}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Step 4 Performs the BASE64URL(UTF8(JWS Protected Header)) operation
      and encoding produces this value (with line break used for display
      purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
eyJhbGciOiJFUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6InBhdCIsIng1dSI6Imh0dHBzOi8vY2VydC5l
eGFtcGxlLmNvbS9wYXQuY2VyIn0


]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Step 5 and Step 6 performs the computation of the digital signature
      of the PAT Signing Input ASCII(BASE64URL(UTF8(JWS Protected Header)) ||
      &lsquo;.&rsquo; || BASE64URL(JWS Payload)) using ES256 as the algorithm
      and the BASE64URL(JWS Signature).</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
4vQEAF_Vlp1Tr6sJmS4pnIKDRmIjH8EZzY5BMT2qJCHD8PmjBktWVnlmbmyHs05G
KauRBdIFnfp3oDPbE0Jq4w

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Step 8 describes how to create the final PAT token, concatenating the
      values in the order Header.Payload.Signature with period
      (&lsquo;.&rsquo;) characters. For the above example values this would
      produce the following (with line breaks between period used for
      readability purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
eyJhbGciOiJFUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6InBhdCIsIng1dSI6Imh0dHBzOi8vY2VydC5l
eGFtcGxlLmNvbS9wYXQuY2VyIn0
.
eyJleHAiOjE0NDM2NDAzNDUsImlhdCI6MTQ0MzIwODM0NSwicG9saWN5aW5mbyI6e
yJmaWx0ZXJpbmciOnsibWFsd2FyZWJsb2NraW5nIjp0cnVlLCJwb2xpY3libG9ja2
luZyI6ZmFsc2V9LCJwcml2YWN5dXJsIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9jb21
taXRtZW50LXRvLXByaXZhY3kvIiwicW5hbWVtaW5pbWl6YXRpb24iOmZhbHNlfSwi
c2VydmVyIjp7ImFkbiI6WyJleGFtcGxlLmNvbSJdfX0
.
4vQEAF_Vlp1Tr6sJmS4pnIKDRmIjH8EZzY5BMT2qJCHD8PmjBktWVnlmbmyHs05G
KauRBdIFnfp3oDPbE0Jq4w
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section anchor="x509-private-key-in-pkcs8-format-for-es256-example"
               title="X.509 Private Key in PKCS#8 Format for ES256 Example**">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
-----BEGIN PRIVATE KEY-----
MIGHAgEAMBMGByqGSM49AgEGCCqGSM49AwEHBG0wawIBAQQgevZzL1gdAFr88hb2
OF/2NxApJCzGCEDdfSp6VQO30hyhRANCAAQRWz+jn65BtOMvdyHKcvjBeBSDZH2r
1RTwjmYSi9R/zpBnuQ4EiMnCqfMPWiZqB4QdbAd0E7oH50VpuZ1P087G
-----END PRIVATE KEY-----
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="x509-public-key-for-es256-example"
               title="X.509 Public Key for ES256 Example**">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
-----BEGIN PUBLIC KEY-----
MFkwEwYHKoZIzj0CAQYIKoZIzj0DAQcDQgAEEVs/o5+uQbTjL3chynL4wXgUg2R9
q9UU8I5mEovUf86QZ7kOBIjJwqnzD1omageEHWwHdBO6B+dFabmdT9POxg==
-----END PUBLIC KEY-----
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example-es256-based-pat-jws-serialization-and-signatures"
             title="Complete JWS JSON Serialization Representation with multiple Signatures">
      <t>The JWS payload used in this example as follows.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "server":{
      "adn":["example.com"]
  },
  "iat":1443208345,
  "exp":1443640345,
  "policyinfo": {
     "filtering": {
         "malwareblocking": true,
         "policyblocking": false
     },
     "qnameminimization":false,
     "privacyurl": "https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/"
  } 
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>This would be serialized to the form (with line break used for
      display purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[{"exp":1443640345,"iat":1443208345,"policyinfo":{
"filtering":{"malwareblocking": true,"policyblocking": false},
"privacyurl":"https://example.com/commitment-to-privacy/",
"qnameminimization":false},"server":{"adn":["example.com"]}}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>The JWS protected Header value used for the first signature is same
      as that used in the example in <xref
      target="example-es256-based-pat-jws-serialization-and-signature"></xref>.
      The X.509 private key used for generating the first signature is same as
      that used in the example in <xref
      target="x509-private-key-in-pkcs8-format-for-es256-example"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The JWS Protected Header value used for the second signature is:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "alg":"ES384",
  "typ":"pat",
  "x5u":"https://cert.audit-example.com/pat.cer"
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The complete JWS JSON Serialization for these values is as follows
      (with line breaks within values for display purposes only):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "payload":
       "eyJleHAiOjE0NDM2NDAzNDUsImlhdCI6MTQ0MzIwODM0NSwicG9saWN5aW5mbyI6
        eyJmaWx0ZXJpbmciOnsibWFsd2FyZWJsb2NraW5nIjp0cnVlLCJwb2xpY3libG9j
        a2luZyI6ZmFsc2V9LCJwcml2YWN5dXJsIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9j
        b21taXRtZW50LXRvLXByaXZhY3kvIiwicW5hbWVtaW5pbWl6YXRpb24iOmZhbHNl
        fSwic2VydmVyIjp7ImFkbiI6WyJleGFtcGxlLmNvbSJdfX0",
  "signatures":[
       {"protected":"eyJhbGciOiJFUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6InBhdCIsIng1dSI6Imh0dHB
        zOi8vY2VydC5leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9wYXQuY2VyIn0",
        "signature": "4vQEAF_Vlp1Tr6sJmS4pnIKDRmIjH8EZzY5BMT2qJCHD8PmjBk
        tWVnlmbmyHs05GKauRBdIFnfp3oDPbE0Jq4w"},
       {"protected":"eyJhbGciOiJFUzM4NCIsInR5cCI6InBhdCIsIng1dSI6Imh0dHB
        zOi8vY2VydC5hdWRpdC1leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9wYXQuY2VyIn0",
        "signature":666ag_mAqDa3Oyxo1DGXUocr0MmRjpXwq8kWp1S21mvs2-kPCIq3
        0xsBJt4apy-sq3VyJgIqzjijoFYURhHvupF0obo-IFUGSZ1YHBCX_MiyBwJQJjtp
        S91ujDatRTtZ"}]
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section anchor="x509-private-key-in-pkcs8-format-for-es384-example"
               title="X.509 Private Key in PKCS#8 format for E384 Example**">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
-----BEGIN PRIVATE KEY-----
MIGHAgEAMBMGByqGSM49AgEGCCqGSM49AwEHBG0wawIBAQQgevZzL1gdAFr88hb2
OF/2NxApJCzGCEDdfSp6VQO30hyhRANCAAQRWz+jn65BtOMvdyHKcvjBeBSDZH2r
1RTwjmYSi9R/zpBnuQ4EiMnCqfMPWiZqB4QdbAd0E7oH50VpuZ1P087G
-----END PRIVATE KEY-----
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="x509-public-key-for-es384-example"
               title="X.509 Public Key for ES384 Example**">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
-----BEGIN PUBLIC KEY-----
MFkwEwYHKoZIzj0CAQYIKoZIzj0DAQcDQgAEEVs/o5+uQbTjL3chynL4wXgUg2R9
q9UU8I5mEovUf86QZ7kOBIjJwqnzD1omageEHWwHdBO6B+dFabmdT9POxg==
-----END PUBLIC KEY-----
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
